It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
How does eating meat or poultry contribute
to the development of antibiotic resistance?
Here's our first story with NutritionFacts
Senior Research Scientist, Dr. Kristine Dennis.
According to
the World Health Organization,
more antibiotics
are fed to farm animals
to prevent disease
and fatten them faster
than are used
to treat sick people.
This can foster the growth of
antibiotic-resistant superbugs
that can then get
transmitted to humans.
As the UK's
Chief Medical Officer
once put it,
"Every inappropriate
or unnecessary use
in animals or agriculture
is potentially signing
a death warrant
for a future patient.”
So, what are they:
miracle drugs or pig food?
Here's how Dr. Greger
framed the issue
in a debate he had
with industry representatives,
including from the
National Pork Producers Council.
To ask if there's a question
between human drug resistance
and livestock antibiotic use
is like asking if there's
human-induced climate change,
or if there's a link
between smoking and lung cancer.
There are a few dissenting
industry scientists on one side,
but then, basically,
every other scientist
on the other.
Both opposing camps
have scientists on their side,
but only one really has
science on their side.
One can just look at who's
on the sides of this debate.
In one corner,
you have
the World Health Organization,
the American Medical
Association,
the American Academy
of Pediatrics,
American Public Health
Association,
another 100
medical and public health
organizations in the country.
On the other side,
you have
the National Turkey Federation,
the National Chicken Council,
the Sheep Industry Association,
the National Pork Producers.
It could not be more stark.
Previously, Dr. Greger discussed
how feeding millions of pounds
of antibiotics
to cows, pigs, and chickens
every year is dangerous,
because it fosters
antibiotic resistance--
not necessarily
because there's a problem
with antibiotic drug residues
getting into the meat itself.
But, turns out,
he may be wrong.
In 2010,
the U.S. Inspector General
slammed the U.S.
Department of Agriculture
for not protecting
the American public
from the contamination of meat
with residual drugs,
pesticides, and heavy metals.
These drug and chemical residues
then find their way
to our dinner plates.
But in order to safeguard
the nation's food supply
from harmful residues,
the USDA,
Food and Drug Administration,
and Environmental
Protection Agency
are supposed to test
for these contaminants,
and prevent adulterated meat
from entering the food supply.
But, based on their review,
the U.S. Inspector General
found that
the National Residue Program
is not accomplishing its mission
of monitoring the food supply
for harmful residues.
Regulators hadn't even
established threshold values
for many dangerous substances,
which has resulted
in contaminated meat
being distributed to consumers.
What potential effects
could the drugs
and toxic metals in meat
have on people who consume it?
Gastrointestinal bleeding,
ulcers, allergic reactions,
serious nerve damage,
severe inflammation,
skin cancers,
internal cancers, jaundice,
kidney failure,
neurotoxicity, and even death.
Doesn't cooking
destroy the drugs, though?
No.
No amount of cooking
will destroy residues.
In fact, in some cases,
heat may actually
break residues down
into components that are even
more harmful to consumers.
The Pew Charitable Trusts
point out
that chemicals
that experts agree
pose a significant
public health hazard
are not routinely tested for,
while others
that pose little risk
are routinely included
in sampling plans.
The USDA does test
for some hazardous drugs though,
and found that only about
1 in 260 samples
of animal products
had drug residue violations.
But that suggests more than
100 million pounds of meat
adulterated with drugs
is served up every year
in the United States alone.
Did you know that
those eating plant-based
have a reduced load of antibiotic
resistance genes in their gut?
Here’s the story.
There are nearly a million salmonella
and campylobacter infections
in children 10 and younger
each year in the United States.
Some of these infections are severe,
causing meningitis and death, and
requiring treatment with antibiotics.
The problem is that there's
an increasing problem of
antibiotic resistance among
these bugs that threatens
our ability to treat them.
Part of the problem is that the same
life-saving miracle-drug antibiotics
are being squandered
for use in food animals
for things like growth promotion
in such unhygienic,
crowded conditions,
which increases the likelihood
that pathogens like salmonella
or campylobacter will
become resistant,
and I've done a bunch
of videos on that.
But there's another problem.
The resistance determinants,
the genes that encode
antibiotic resistance,
may be transmitted from food animals
to humans through the food supply.
See, most resistant bacteria
have mobile genetic elements,
like these little circles
of DNA called plasmids,
that carry the resistance genes
that they can then pass on
to other bacteria, including
those in our own gut.
Food animals are, therefore,
a reservoir of antibiotic resistance
genes and a potential
vector for transmission
of antibiotic resistance genes to
the human intestinal microbiome.
In this study, transfer of an
antibiotic resistance plasmid
from an E. coli originating
from a chicken raised for meat
to human gut bugs was
assessed by using a model
that mimics the human intestines.
And it happened within two hours.
This spread of antibiotic resistance
genes presents an alarming scenario,
a growing concern that antibiotic
resistant bacteria present on food
can transfer their resistance genes
to the inherent gut microbiome
of the consumer.
But you don't know
until you put it to the test.
Assessing antibiotic resistance
gene loads in vegan vs. vegetarian
vs. omnivore gut bacteria.
You'd think the results
might be obvious,
but antibiotic resistance
genes are spread due to
manure application on agricultural
fields of fruits and vegetables.
Yes, massive antibiotic use in
animal farming is considered
as the greatest contributor to the
presence of antibiotic-resistant
bacteria in food of animal origin:
meats, eggs, and dairy.
Nevertheless, sewage from
treated animals may impact
on vegetables grown
on fertilized fields,
but it was largely unknown
whether, and to what extent,
antibiotic-resistant bacteria are
being transferred to vegetables
and then to the human gut until now.
Researchers looked for antibiotic-
resistant genes against sulfa drugs
like bactrim, tetracyclines,
penicillins and cephalosporins,
and streptomycin-type antibiotics
and both omnivores and vegetarians
showed a signigicantly higher
antibiotic-resistant
gene load in their guts
as compared with vegans.
There wasn't a significant difference
between omnivores and vegetarians,
but significantly lower loads in
vegans compared to omnivores,
and vegans compared to
vegetarians, the first evidence
that a vegan lifestyle
is associated with
a reduced load of human
gut antibiotic-resistant genes,
but not the last.
Fewer tetracycline resistance
genes in vegan guts and
more vancomycin resistance genes
in the guts of those who eat meat.
No surprise, since they found
a correlation between
tetracycline resistance genes
and the intake of eggs,
milk, and cheese ---
I like how there are so many
types of milk these days
they have to specify
"milk from animal sources."
And a higher incidence of
vancomycin resistance genes
was found in consumers
of eggs, poultry, fish, and seafood.
And vancomycin is one of our
antibiotics of last resort, used to
treat serious life-threatening
strep and staph infections
like MRSA (M-R-S-A).
Despite the links to dairy and
eggs, just cutting out meat
has indeed been shown to offer
an advantage in some studies,
as bacteria obtained from meat-eater
poop samples showed resistance
to a greater number of antibiotics
and carried more tested
antibiotic resistance genes compared
to the vegan or vegetarian poop.
Finally today,
we look at how tainted chicken may result in
more than a million urinary tract infections
in American women every year.
In my video on antibiotic resistance
genes, I explored how more
were found in the guts of those
who eat meat, dairy, and eggs
than those who eat
completely plant-based.
But does the transfer of bacteria
from animal foods in the human gut
result in differences in
actual clinical outcomes --
other than food poisoning, of course?
Foodborne bacteria sicken about
350 million people every year,
and most of that can be traced
to meat, dairy products, and eggs.
Besides food poisoning, though,
what about extraintestinal infections,
infections outside the digestive tract,
for example, due to pathogenic
and antibiotic-resistant E. coli
from retail chicken breasts?
Infections where, though?
The urinary tract.
There's a type of E. coli
called ST131,
which is a foodborne
uropathogen, meaning it causes
urinary tract infections, most of
which are just bladder infections,
which typically amount to little
more than a painful annoyance,
but can become invasive and
spread up into the kidneys
and invade the bloodstream
and end your life.
E. coli ST131 emerged explosively
in the last 20 years or so
to become the most important
multidrug-resistant uropathogen
in circulation today.
Urinary tract infections
are caused principally
by ascending E. coli infection via
an intestine-stool-urethra route,
meaning these E. coli that cause
UTIs, called extra-intestinal
pathogenic E. coli or ExPEC
bacteria, start out in the colon,
make it to the anus and
then make their way
up into the urethra,
then into your bladder.
How do they get into your
intestines in the first place?
That's where the chicken comes in.
The role of poultry-meat can be
to introduce the ExPEC bacteria,
allowing it to colonize in the rectums
of consumers, lying in wait until
an opportunity to cause infection
presents itself, for example,
thrusting from sexual intercourse
can introduce the bacteria
into the urethra.
The time lag between human
ExPEC acquisition in the intestine
and the bladder infection has been
the fundamental challenge
linking the two, but we now
have strong evidence
that a substantial portion
of the ST131 strains
infecting humans
originate from poultry.
But they couldn't tell whether
any single infection arose
from direct exposure to
contaminated poultry or
indirectly from chicken meat from
human-to-human transmission
from, say, a partner who ate
some contaminated poultry.
What percentage of human
UTIs arise from poultry?
Researchers analyzed E. coli
isolates from urine samples
from patients with suspected UTIs
and compared them to the bacteria
on retail meat samples
in the same region,
using DNA fingerprinting techniques.
They found that about a fifth
of E. coli isolates from suspected
cases of UTIs belonged to types
found in local retail poultry.
21% might not sound like a lot,
but E. coli UTIs are one of
the most common infectious
diseases in the United States,
affecting approximately
seven million women,
so contaminated chicken may
result in more than a million UTIs
in American women every year.
This may explain why women
infected with multidrug-resistant
E. coli reported more frequent
chicken consumption,
putting them at nearly
four times the odds,
though frequent consumption
of pork was also a risk factor.
Wait. Is it found in pigs, too?
Human ExPEC,
those extraintestinal
E. coli that cause UTIs, have
also been identified on pig farms,
in pigs, and in retail pork meat,
albeit at considerably lower levels
than in poultry or chicken meat.
So chicken is riskiest, pork less so,
and beef could be considered
the safest from a UTI standpoint,
since cattle don't appear
to be a reservoir of these
particular types of E. coli.
OK, well, if meat, including poultry
and pork, is the major reservoir
for these UTI bacteria, then
vegetarians, who avoid meat,
should theoretically
suffer less exposure.
However, no study thus far has
examined whether vegetarian diets
reduce the risk
of UTIs until now:
a prospective study on the
risk of urinary tract infection
in vegetarians versus
non-vegetarians.
Well, if around 20% are
tied to retail chicken meat,
no surprise that eating vegetarian
is associated with around
20% lower risk of UTIs,
particularly in women.
And this association was
independent of diseases
and predisposing risk factors
like hypertension, diabetes,
and high cholesterol,
meaning it's not just due
to the fact that vegetarians
had less diabetes or something.
What about buying
organic chicken?
Bacteria swabbed from
chicken labeled organic
harbored less antibiotic
resistant bacteria, but no --
no less likely to be contaminated
with ExPEC UTI bacteria.
These findings suggest that retail
chicken products in the United States,
even if they're labeled organic,
pose a potential health threat
to consumers because
they're contaminated with
extensively antibiotic-resistant
E. coli, including the ones
that cause UTIs.
To date only the Jack-in-the-Box
E. coli, like O157:H7,
are considered food adulterants,
meaning it's not legal to
knowingly sell contaminated meat.
Why don't they do the same
with the ExPEC bugs now that
there's such strong evidence
they're infecting so many women?
Well, in a survey of retail
chicken breasts collected
widely across the United States,
14.3% of the E. coli they found
appeared to be ExPEC.
Given that E. coli can
be found in about 90%
of retail turkey and chicken
products, that would mean
the industry would have to dump
literally billions of pounds
of chicken breasts every year.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.